<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine deuout and godly petitions called the Iesus psalter</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14570.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3135</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143049</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143049</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28194</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04442)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28194)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1880:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine deuout and godly petitions called the Iesus psalter</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[St. Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint information from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"With Priviledge."</note>
                  <note>A-B¹².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Prayer-books and devotions --  English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28194:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CERTAINE DEVOVT AND GODLY PETITIONS. called the IESVS PSALTER.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>IHS</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <q>There is no other Name vnder Heauen giuen vnto men, in which we must be ſaued. <bibl>Act. 4. Verſ. 12.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>With Priuiledge 1624</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:28194:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISMENT.</head>
            <p>BEGINNE your Pſalter with deuout kneeling, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with bowing to Ieſus, and ſay thus as followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <q>In the name of <hi>IESVS</hi> let euerie knee bowe, of the celeſtialls, terrestrials, and infernals: and euerie tongue con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe, that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, is in the glory of God the Father.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And at the end, either of the firſt Fiue, Ten, or laſt Fifteene, ſay:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt humbled himſelfe, being made obedient vnto death: euen the death of the Croſſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="prayer">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:28194:2"/>
            <head>THE FIRST PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Haue mercy on me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Haue mercy on me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Haue mercy on me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Haue mercy on me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Haue mercy on me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Haue mercy on me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Haue mercy on me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Haue mercy on me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Haue mercy on me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Haue mercy on me.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV haue mercy vpon me, and forgiue me the great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences which I haue done in the ſight of thee.</p>
            <p>Grant me grace Ieſu, for the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:28194:3"/>loue of thee, to deſpiſe ſinne, and all worldly vanity.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu I beſeech thee: turne their vices into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glory.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeech thee, and for thy giorious Name, Ieſu.</p>
            <p>O holy Trinity, One True God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="prayer">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:28194:3"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Helpe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Helpe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Helpe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Helpe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Helpe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Helpe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Helpe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Helpe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Helpe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Helpe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV helpe me to ouercome all temptations to ſinne: and the malice of my ghoſtly enemy.</p>
            <p>To ſpend my time in vertue and labour acceptable to thee: to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:28194:4"/>repreſſe the motions of my fleſh, in ſlouth, gluttony, &amp; carnality.</p>
            <p>To haue my hart enumoured of vertue, and the glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thee: to haue good name and fame, Ieſu, to thy honour, &amp; to the comfort of me.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu I beſeech thee: turne their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I beſeech thee, and for thy glorious Name, Ieſu.</p>
            <p>O holy Trinitie, One True God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="prayer">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:28194:4"/>
            <head>THE THIRD PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV ſtrengthen me in ſoule &amp; body, to execute the workes of vertue to the pleaſure of thee: wherby I may come to thy euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioy, and felicity.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:28194:5"/>
            <p>Grant me firme purpoſe, moſt mercifull Ieſu, to amend my life, &amp; to recompence for thoſe years which I haue miſſpent to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of thee, in euil thoughts, delectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, conſentings, wordes, workes, and euill cuſtomes.</p>
            <p>Alſo in breaking thy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, wherby I haue deſerued damnation, and thine emnity.</p>
            <p>Make mine hart obedient to fulfill thy will, and ready to doe for thy loue the workes of pitty.</p>
            <p>Grant me the ſeauen giftes of the holy Ghoſt: the eight Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes: the foure Cardinall vertues: and in receauing of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, deuoutly to diſpoſe me.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, Ieſu I beſeech thee: turne their vices into vertues, &amp; make them true obſeruers of thy law, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:28194:5"/>louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glory.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I beſeech thee, and for thy glorious Name, Ieſu.</p>
            <p>O holy Trinity, One True God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="prayer">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:28194:6"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Comfort me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Comfort me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Comfort me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Comfort me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Comfort me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Comfort me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Comfort me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Comfort me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Comfort me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Comfort me.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV comfort me, and giue me grace to haue my greateſt ioy and pleaſure in thee.</p>
            <p>Send me heauenly medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ghoſtly ſweetnes, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:28194:6"/>of thy glory.</p>
            <p>Rauiſh my ſoule with bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deſire of thy heauenly ioy, where I ſhal euerlaſtingly dwell with thee.</p>
            <p>Grant me, ſweet Sauiour Ieſu, contempt of all wicked plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, full of ſinne and miſery.</p>
            <p>Grant me remembrance of my ſaluation, with feare of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Alſo remembrance of thy goodneſſe, thy gifts, and great kindneſſe shewed to me.</p>
            <p>Reduce into my mynd, my ſinnes and wickednes, wherby I haue offended thee.</p>
            <p>Grant me the ſpirit of perfect penance, contrition, confeſſion, and ſatisfaction, to obtaine thy grace, and from filthy ſinne to purge me.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:28194:7"/>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, Ieſu I beſeech thee: turne their vices into vertues, &amp; make them true obſeruers of thy law, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I beſeech thee, and for thy glorious Name, Ieſu.</p>
            <p>O holy Trinity, One True God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noster. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="prayer">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:28194:7"/>
            <head>THE FIFTH PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV make me conſtant and ſtable in faith, hope, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: with continuance in vertue, and deſire not to offend thee.</p>
            <p>Make me ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to remember thy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:28194:8"/>paſſion, and bitter paines, which thou ſufferedſt for me.</p>
            <p>Send me perfect patience, in all tribulation and aduerſitie.</p>
            <p>Preſerue me from Pride, Ire, Enuie, Couetouſneſſe, and from all other offences contrary to thy holy Law.</p>
            <p>The Catholique Obſeruances of the Church, make me to keep truly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Make my Soule obedient to holie Doctrine, and to thinges pertayning to my ghoſtly weale, for the loue of thee.</p>
            <p>Suffer no falſe delight of this deceaueable life, by fleſhly tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, &amp; fraud of the Enemy to blind me.</p>
            <p>Till the houre of my death, my fiue Senſes, Ieſu keep I beſeech thee.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:28194:8"/>
            <p>From exceſſe in Speaking, in Feeding, and Working euill, preſerue my frailty.</p>
            <p>Haue mercie on all ſinners, Ieſu I beſeech thee: turne their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I beſeech thee, and for thy glorious Name, Ieſu.</p>
            <p>O holy Trinity, One True God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt humbled himſelf, being made obedient vnto death: eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the death of the Croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="prayer">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:28194:9"/>
            <head>THE SIXT PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Enlighten me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Enlighten me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Enlighten me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Enlighten me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Enlighten me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Enlighten me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Enlighten me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Enlighten me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Enlighten me.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Enlighten me.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV enlighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me with ghoſtly wiſedome to know thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thoſe thinges which are moſt acceptable to thee.</p>
            <p>Graunt me grace to giue good
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:28194:9"/>example, profitable to ſoules, that none be hurt by me: and to help thoſe with good counſell, who haue offended thee.</p>
            <p>Make me proceede from ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to vertue, vntill ſuch time, that I shall clearely ſee thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty.</p>
            <p>Let me not returne to thoſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which I haue ſorrowed for, and by confeſſion haue accuſed my ſelfe off.</p>
            <p>The horrible ſentence, of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe death, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>err<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble iudgement of damnation, thy wrath, ire, and indignation mercifull Lord, let neuer fall vpon me.</p>
            <p>Thy Mercy and thy Merits. O my Sauiour, be euer betweene them and me.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on al ſinners Ieſu I beſeech thee: turne their vices
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:28194:10"/>into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I beſeech thee, and for thy glorious Name Ieſu.</p>
            <p>O holy Trinity, One True God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="prayer">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:28194:10"/>
            <head>THE SEAVENTH PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dread thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dread thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dread thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dread thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dread thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dread thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dread thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dread thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dread thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dread thee.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV grant me grace inwardly to dread thee, and to eſchew all thoſe thinges, wherby I may offend thee.</p>
            <p>Thy Bleſſed Mother be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatreſſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:28194:11"/>for me: and purchaſe me a contrite hart for that wherin I haue offended thee.</p>
            <p>Remoue my ſinfull diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which dull my hart, and like vnto lead do oppreſſe me.</p>
            <p>All thy Saints pray for me, that I be not ſeparated from thee, and from their Bleſſed fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship in thy heauenly Citty.</p>
            <p>Let me not forget good Lord, the riches of thy goodnes, of thy patie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, of thy long ſufferance and benignity.</p>
            <p>Let the theatning of paine &amp; and torment, which shall fall vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinners, the loſſe of thy loue, and of thy heauenlie inheritance euer terrify me to offend thee.</p>
            <p>Suffer me not to lye in ſinne, but call me ſoone to penance: and when I shal haue diſpleaſed thee,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:28194:11"/>haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, Ieſu I beſeech thee: turne their vices into vertues; &amp; make them true obſeruers of thy law, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I beſeech thee, and for thy glorious Name, Ieſu.</p>
            <p>O holy Trinity, One True God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noster. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="prayer">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:28194:12"/>
            <head>THE EIGHT PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to loue thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to loue thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to loue thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to loue thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to loue thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to loue thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to loue thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to loue thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to loue thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to loue thee.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV grant me grace truly to loue thee, for thy endleſſe goodneſſe; and for thoſe giftes which I haue receaued, and truſt to receaue of thee.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:28194:12"/>
            <p>Lord when I offend, ſtrike me not with ſuddaine death, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee.</p>
            <p>Let the remembrance of thy Gentlenes and Patience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer all Malice and wretched Deſires in me.</p>
            <p>Drawe me Lord to thee, by perfect Loue and Charity.</p>
            <p>By breaking of thy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements I haue deſpiſed thee: grant me good Lord, in keeping of them, as greatly to honour thee.</p>
            <p>From leſſer ſinnes, that I fall not into the greater, Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me.</p>
            <p>Doe with me according to thy mercy, &amp; not according to my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery: withdraw thy ſword of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, for thy great mercy and pitty.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:28194:13"/>
            <p>Grant me Lord to be the child of ſaluation, in body and ſoule to haue glorification, cleere ſight, and fruition of thy Diuinity, and euer preſently to ſee the glorious Trinity.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu I beſeech thee: turne their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I beſeech thee, and for thy glorious Name, Ieſu.</p>
            <p>O holy Trinity, One True God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter, Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="prayer">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:28194:13"/>
            <head>THE NINTH PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my death.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my death.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my death.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my death.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my death.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my death.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my death.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my death.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my death.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my death.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV grant me grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member perfectly the danger of my death, and the great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count which I muſt then giue to thee: and ſo diſpoſe me, that my
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:28194:14"/>ſoule be acceptable to thee, and to thy glorious Mother, the B. Virgin Mary.</p>
            <p>Then with the aſſiſtance of the glorious Angel S. Michael, deliuer me from the daunger of my ghoſtly enemie. And thou my good Angell, I beſeech thee then to helpe me.</p>
            <p>Then good Lord, remember thy mercy: and for mine offences turne not thy louely face fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me.</p>
            <p>O my Lord, be a mercifull, kind and meeke Iudge vnto me, at that dreadfull houre.</p>
            <p>That I may not heare the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of thy righteouſnes, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I appeale to thy mercy.</p>
            <p>Thy mercy exceedeth thy iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement: and to vs ſinners it is ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, when we cry hartily to thee.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:28194:14"/>
            <p>At that dreadfull houre, help vs moſt mercifull Lord, who for the time now call for mercy.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu I beſeech thee: turne their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glory.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I beſeech thee, and for thy glorious Name, Ieſu.</p>
            <p>O holy Trinitie, One True God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="prayer">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:28194:15"/>
            <head>THE TENTH PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Send me here my Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Send me here my Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Send me here my Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Send me here my Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Send me here my Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Send me here my Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Send me here my Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Send me here my Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Send me here my Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Send me here my Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV ſend me heere my Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory: and preſerue me from thoſe torments of fire, which euer ſhall puniſh ſinne and iniquity.</p>
            <p>Let full hope of thine helpe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:28194:15"/>alwayes abide in me, that I neuer fall in deſperation of thy endleſſe mercy.</p>
            <p>O Mother of God, Patriarkes, Prophets, Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, Martyrs, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſors, Virgins, Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, Matrons, and Innocents. I offer my ſelfe to your merits, and beſeech you to pray for me, and at my paſſing, helpe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect me.</p>
            <p>With thy Sacraments O Lord thon recomfort me: and bring me to the Kingdome of endleſſe felicity.</p>
            <p>My Lord Ieſu crucified for me, by the merits of thy glorious paſſion, I beſeech thee, graunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe Petitions which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> asked of thee.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> Ieſu I beſeech thee: turne th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:28194:16"/>into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glory.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I beſeech thee, and for thy glorious Name, Ieſu.</p>
            <p>O holy Trinity, One True God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath humbled himſelf, being made obedient vnto dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h: eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the death of the Croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="prayer">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:28194:16"/>
            <head>THE ELEAVENTH PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to flie euill company.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to flie euill company.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to flie euill company.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to flie euill company.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to flie euill company.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to flie euill company.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to flie euill company.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to flie euill company.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to flie euill company.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to flie euill company.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV grant me gace to flie euill company, and when I come among them, for thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious paſſion I beſeech thee, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me, that no occaſion of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:28194:17"/>mortall ſinne ouercome me: and ſend me ghoſtly comfort, by ſuch as be true louers of thee.</p>
            <p>Keepe my mouth, good Lord, from ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derous ſpeaches, lying, falſe witneſſe-bearing, curſing, ſwearing, vncharitable chiding, diſſolute laughing, and wordes of vanitie.</p>
            <p>Make me, Bleſſed Lord, with dread to remember, that thou preſently heareſt me, &amp; who of all my wordes ſhalt iudge me.</p>
            <p>Suffer not my hart to be light of credit, in hearing detraction, obloquy, rancor, and ire.</p>
            <p>Ieſu repreſſe in me al inordinate affection of carnality: &amp; where I haue by euil fellowſhippe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, meekely I aske mercy of thee: and I beſeech thee to help all that crie to thee for mercy.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:28194:17"/>
            <p>Thy power protect me, thy wiſdome direct me, thy Fatherly pitty correct me.</p>
            <p>Send me a gratious life, and a Bleſſed ending: and thy paſſion preſerue me from euerlaſting damnation, and terrour of mine Enemy.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, Ieſu I beſeech thee: turne their vices into vertues, &amp; make them true obſeruers of thy law, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glory <hi>&amp;c. as before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="prayer">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:28194:18"/>
            <head>THE TWELFTH PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue me grace to call for helpe to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue me grace to call for helpe to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue me grace to call for helpe to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue me grace to call for helpe to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue me grace to call for helpe to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue me grace to call for helpe to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue me grace to call for helpe to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue me grace to call for helpe to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue me grace to call for helpe to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue me grace to call for helpe to thee.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV grant me grace, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the time of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to cal for helpe to thee: and then with faithfull mind to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy paſſion, which thou
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:28194:18"/>ſufferedſt for me.</p>
            <p>Then, moſt mercifull Lord, keep my ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all conſent to ſinne: &amp; for the very true loue of thee, then let ſinne appeare ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and abhominable to me.</p>
            <p>Let the remembrance of the paines of hell and damnation, ſo horrible, &amp; terrible, and full of thine anger, with the merites of thy meeke patience, through charity and chaſtity, mitigate the proneſſe to ſinne &amp; fraylty in me.</p>
            <p>In my temptations, Lord I beſeech thee, helpe me: for the tender loue that thou dideſt ſhew to thy Mother, and ſhe to thee.</p>
            <p>Repell the power of my ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie aduerſaries, which intend the damnation of me.</p>
            <p>Inhabit my ſoule, O Sauiour,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:28194:19"/>which with al humble ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, deſireth the Bleſſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thee.</p>
            <p>Make me pure in ſpirit, meeke in ſpeaking, patient in ſuffering, hungrie of righteous working, &amp; merciful to all thoſe that be in miſery.</p>
            <p>Make me peaceable in conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, cleane in hart with holy meditation, and ioyfully to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Perſecution for the cauſe of thee.</p>
            <p>Let al my powers, and deſires be ruled according to the will of thee: and all my petitions orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to thy wiſedome, and to the euerlaſting profit of me.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, <hi>&amp;c. as before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="prayer">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:28194:19"/>
            <head>THE THIRTENTH PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in Vertue.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in Vertue.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in Vertue.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in Vertue.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in Vertue.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in Vertue.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in Vertue.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in Vertue.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Make me to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in Vertue.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV make me perſeuerant in the Bleſſed ſeruice of thee: in holy cuſtome and vertuous oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation, Lord keep my ſoule and my body.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:28194:20"/>
            <p>Make me to flie ſinful delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: &amp; patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to ſuffer iniuries and rebukes, in recompence of my diſobedient hart to thee.</p>
            <p>Prouide good Lord, that life for me, which thou knoweſt to be moſt to thy honour, and to my eternall felicity.</p>
            <p>Fill my hart with contrition, and mine eyes with teares, that I neuer be forſaken of thee.</p>
            <p>Awake my dull ſoule from ſleep of ſinne, and ſend me help from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, my Bleſſed Sauiour, to ouercome the old ſerpent with all his crafte, by exerciſe of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and ſpeciall grace of thee.</p>
            <p>The Angels of light, deliuer mee from the Angels of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; from their great cruelty.</p>
            <p>Let thy obedience, Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for my obſtinacie; thy
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:28194:20"/>abſtinence, for my ſuperfluity, thy meekeneſſe and thy patience, for my pride, ireful hate and emnity.</p>
            <p>Thy charity for my malice, thy deuotion for my dulneſſe, thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hart for my vnkindneſſe, thy holy death for my wretched life, and for all my miſery.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu I beſeech thee: turne their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glory <hi>&amp;c. as before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="prayer">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:28194:21"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTENTH PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Grant me grace to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV grant me grace, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the time of prayer, to fixe my mind on thee, and then to remember my wretchednes, &amp; faithfully to cal for help to thee.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:28194:21"/>
            <p>And at that time to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the perils of body and ſoule which I haue eſcaped, and the benefits that I haue receaued through thy great charity: and with all my hart, Lord, then to giue praiſe to thee.</p>
            <p>In this prayer, I thanke thee for all the creatures which thou haſt made to help man, and that thou haſte made him to thine Image: &amp; finally in thy glory to honour thee.</p>
            <p>The motions of my running mind, the deſires of my vnſtable hart, in the time of prayer to ſtop, and ſtay I beſeech thee.</p>
            <p>Repreſſe the power of my ghoſtly Enemies, when they ſhall drawe my mind from ghoſtly weale, to any imaginations of vanity.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:28194:22"/>
            <p>With the hand of thy ſeruent loue, then I beſeech thee to take me, and ſtrengthen me in thy power: and with thy goodneſſe to glad me.</p>
            <p>Keepe me ſo exerciſed in good workes, that my prayers may be acceptable to thee.</p>
            <p>Heare now, ſweete Sauiour Ieſu, heare the voyce of a ſinner, which would faine loue thee, and with my hart as greatly pleaſe thee, as euer it hath offended thee: and if it pleaſe thy grace, more largely to recompence it, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee.</p>
            <p>Ieſu ſaue mine enemies from thy enmitie, and forgiue them that wherin they haue offended me: like as I would be forgiuen in thoſe thinges, wherein I haue offended thee.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:28194:22"/>
            <p>Lord helpe all thoſe which haue holpen mee, or prayed for me, or ſhewed to me any deed of pitty.</p>
            <p>Thy Grace, O Lord, &amp; the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of thy pretious bloud, defend me from the ſtriking Angel, and the ſpirit of peſtilence, and cauſe him to ouer paſſe me.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu I beſeech thee: turne their vices into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glory <hi>&amp;c. as before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="prayer">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:28194:23"/>
            <head>THE FIFTEENTH PETITION.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue mee grace to order my life to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue mee grace to order my life to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue mee grace to order my life to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue mee grace to order my life to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue mee grace to order my life to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue mee grace to order my life to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue mee grace to order my life to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue mee grace to order my life to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue mee grace to order my life to thee.</item>
               <item>Ieſu, Ieſu, Ieſu, Giue mee grace to order my life to thee.</item>
            </list>
            <p>IESV giue me grace to order my life, and the workes of my body and ſoule, with actuall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to ſerue thee, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of thy infinite ioy and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicity.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:28194:23"/>
            <p>The water and bloud which ranne from thy Bleſſed harte, waſh my ſoule from ſinne and iniquiy: and purchaſe to me aboundance of grace, faithfully to ſerue thee.</p>
            <p>O my Lord, my life, my might, and my light, leade me, feed me, and ſpeed me, in the pilgrimage of this mortality.</p>
            <p>Grant me Lord, by the merits of thy paſſion, and vertue of thy moſt excellent and glorious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity, whatſoeuer thy wiſdom knoweth moſt expedient for me, which my miſerable life is not worthy to obtaine of thee.</p>
            <p>At the houre of my Death, when I ſhall be accuſed before thee for the death that thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feredſt for ſinners, haue mercy on me.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28194:24"/>
            <p>Breake my froward hart and make it obedient to thee: &amp; from ſuddaine and vnprouided death, Lord preſerue me.</p>
            <p>Grant me grace to depart with contempt of this world: &amp; with ioyfull hart to come to thee.</p>
            <p>Let the remembrance of thy paſſion, make mee ioyfully to beare temptation, &amp; tribulation for the loue of thee.</p>
            <p>Make mee moſt to loue that ioyful life, that immortall glory, moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bliſſe &amp; endleſſe fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie, which is ordained in thy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nly Kingdome for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of thee.</p>
            <p>By the vertue of thy Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Natiuity, Paſſion, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, grant me theſe ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, which I haue made to thee, in this Inuocation and Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:28194:24"/>of thee.</p>
            <p>And by the interceſſion of thy moſt entirely beloued Mother, purchaſe to me, a gratious life, &amp; Bleſſed ending, free from debt, and deadly ſinne, I beſeech thee: and after my bodylie death, euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, with endleſſe bliſſe &amp; felicity.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on al ſinners, <hi>&amp;c. as before</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf, being made obedient vnto death: euen the death of the Croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater noster. Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:28194:25"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>SVS, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ee b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e of the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> Terreſtria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe that our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is in the glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Father.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>The End of the <hi>IESVS</hi> Pſalter.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
